Finding Aid for the Montague Gowthorpe Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Gowthorpe, Montague Collection
multiple
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0177
7.5 linear_feet
The Montague F. Gowthorpe Opera Collection was created a period of years by Montague F. Gowthorpe chairman of the Detroit Symphony and one of the original vice-presidents at Paramount Pictures. Gowthorpe was born in Kings Lyn, England in 1898 and was a lifetime devotee of opera which he regarded as the highest form of art and entertainment. After his death in 1980 this collection was passed to his niece, Bonnie Lamar, MD of Tennessee. She donated it to Special Collections in 1998.
The collection consists of 200 reel-to-reel tapes recorded by Mr. Gowthorpe from radio. The tapes were recorded at 3 ¾ and 7 ½ speeds from the years of 1959 to 1968 though the bulk of the recordings were made in the early 1960’s.
The last box of the collection contains 48 libretto books collected and annotated by Mr. Gowthorpe to accompany the recordings he made.
- Audio Reel to Reels
  - Adventures in Good Music 1A –Music by Forgotten Composers (Box 1)
  - Adventures in Good Music 1B –Music by Forgotten Composers (Box 1)
  - Adventures in Good Music 2A –What’s in a Name (Box 1)
  - Adventures in Good Music 2B –What’s in a Name (Box 1)
  - Adventures in Good Music 3A (Box 1)
  - Adventures in Good Music 3B (Box 1)
  - Adventures in Good Music 4A –Music Inspired by Nature, Calls of Birds (Box 1)
  - Adventures in Good Music 4B –Music Inspired by Nature (Box 1)
  - Aida –Verdi Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Herbert von Karajan (3) (Box 1)
  - Alcestis –Willibald von Gluck Performed by the New York Metropolitan Opera, Conductor Kurt Adler, February 11, 1961 (3) (Box 1)
  - Ariadne auf Naxos –R. Strauss (3) (Box 1)
  - Andrea Chenier –Giordano Performed by the La Scala Chorus and Orchestra, Conductor Oliviero Fabritiis (2) (Box 1)
  - Barber of Seville –Rossini Performed by the Philharmonica Orchestra, Conductor Alceo Galliera (2) (Box 1)
  - Beethoven Concerto #1 for Piano and Orchestra (Box 1)
  - Beethoven Symphony #5 in C Minor, Opus 67 Performed by the Concertgebouw Orchestra of Amsterdam, Conductor Erich Kleiber (Box 1)
  - La Boheme –Puccini Preformed by the La Scala Chorus and Orchestra, Conductor Antonio Votto, November 11, 1959 (2) (Box 1)
  - Boris Godounoff –Moussorgsky Performed by the Vienna State Orchestra, Conductor Hermann Scherchen (3) (Box 1)
  - Simon Boccanegra –Verdi Performed by the Orchestra of the Opera House, Rome, Conductor Gabrielle Santini (3) (Box 1)
  - Four Brahms Symphonies Performed by the NBC Orchestra, Conductor Arturo Toscanini (Box 1)
  - Don Carlo –Verdi Performed by the Orchestra E. Coro di Romo Della Radiotelevisione Italiana, Conductor Fernando Previtali (3) (Box 1)
  - Carmen –Bizet Performed by the L’Orchestre et Choeurs de L’Opera Comique, Paris, Conductor Albert Wolff (2) (Box 1)
  - Enrico Caruso with the Victor Symphony Orchestra (Box 1)
  - Cavelliera Rusticana –Mascagni, December 2, 1959 (2) (Box 1)
  - Cosi Fan Tutti –Mozart Performed by Orchestra Glyndeboure Mozart Opera Festival, 1935 Conductor Fritz Busch (3) (Box 2)
  - Daughter of the Regiment –Ponizetti, February 27, 1960 (2) (Box 2)
  - Elektra –R. Strauss Conductor Joseph Rosenstock (2) (Box 2)
  - Ernani –Verdi Performed by the Orchestra Coro Della Radiotelevisione Italiana, Conductor Fernando Previtali (2) (Box 2)
  - Eugen Onegin –Tchaikovsky Performed by the Orchestra of the National Opera, Belgrade, Conductor Oscar Danon (3) (Box 2)
  - L’Elisir d’Amore –Donizetti Performed by the Chorus and Orchestra of Maggio Musicale Fiorentino (2) (Box 2)
  - Falstaff –Verdi, November 5, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Faust –Gounod Performed by the Orchestra Théatre National de L’Opera, Conductor André Cluytens, November 13, 1962. Two copies (3) (Box 2)
  - Fidelio –Beethoven Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Wilhelm Furtwänger (2) (Box 2)
  - Die Fledermaus –R. Strauss Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Clemens Krausss (2) (Box 2)
  - The Flying Dutchman –Wagner Performed by the Bayreuth Festival Orchestra, Conductor Joseph Keilberth (3) (Box 2)
  - La Forza del Destino –Verdi Performed by the Orchestra L’Academia DiSanta Cecilia in Rome, Conductor Francesco Molinari-Pradelli Two copies (3) (Box 2)
  - Gianni Schicchi –Puccini Performed by the Orchestra Opera House in Rome, Conductor Gabriele Santini (3) (Box 3)
  - La Gioconda –Ponchielli Performed by the Orchestra radio Italiana of Turin, Conductor Antonino Votto (3) (Box 3)
  - La Gioconda –Ponchielli, March 28, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Don Giovanni –Mozart Performed by the New York Metropolitan Opera (3) (Box 3)
  - Don Giovanni –Mozart Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Joseph Krips (2) (Box 3)
  - Götterdämmerung –Wagner Performed by the Oslo Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Ǿlvin Fjeldstad, February 14, 1959 (2) (Box 3)
  - Götterdämmerung –Wagner Performed by the Oslo Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Ǿlvin Fjeldstad, January 21, 1960 (5) (Box 3)
  - Gypsy Baron –J. Strauss Performed by the Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Otto Ackermann (Box 3)
  - Immortal Classics –Dance and Music (Box 3)
  - Immortal Classics –Keyboard and Piano (Box 3)
  - L’Italiano in Algeri –Rossini Performed on C.B.E. Radio, July 16, 1960 (3) (Box 3)
  - Jupiter, Symphony #41 in C Major –Mozart, July 27, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Lohengrin –Wagner Performed by the Metropolitan Opera, Conductor Thomas Schippers, February 1, 1959 (4) (Box 3)
  - Lucia Lammermoor –Donizetti Performed by the Orchestra and Chorus of Florence May Festival, Conductor Tullio Serafin, November 13, 1959 (2) (Box 3)
  - Macbeth –Verdi Performed by the Metropolitan Opera Orchestra and Chorus, Conductor Erich Leinsdorf (2) (Box 3)
  - Madame Butterfly –Puccini Performed by the Orchestra Santa Cecelia in Rome, Conductor Alberto Erede (3) (Box 3)
  - The Magic Flute –Mozart Performed by the Rias Chamber Choir and Symphony Orchestra in Berlin, Conductor Ferenc Fricsay (3) (Box 3)
  - Manon –Massenet Performed by L’Orchestre et Choers de L’Opera Comique in Paris, Conductor Albert Wolff (2) (Box 4)
  - Manon Lescaut –Puccini Performed by the Orchestra of Academia di Santa Cecelia in Rome, Conductor Francesco Molinari-Pradelli (2) (Box 4)
  - Max at the Met –Max Miller (Box 4)
  - Medea –L. Cherubini Performed by the Orchestra and Chorus La Scala, Conductor Tullio Serafin (2) (Box 4)
  - Die Meistersinger von Nürnberg –Wagner Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Hans Knappertsbuch (5) (Box 4)
  - Mireille –Gounod Performed by the Festival D’Aix-en-Provence Orchestre de la Société des Concerts du Conservatoire, Conductor André Cluytens (3) (Box 4)
  - Norma –V. Bellini Performed by the Orchestra and Chorus Teatro Alla Scala in Milan, Conductor Tullio Serafin (3) (Box 4)
  - Le Nozze di Figaro –Mozart Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic, Conductor Erich Kleiber, December 2, 1959 (3) (Box 4)
  - Nutcracker –Tchaikovsky Performed by the Minneapolis Symphony Orchestra, Conductor Antal Dorati (2) (Box 4)
  - Operatic Arias –Mantovani (Box 4)
  - Otello –Verdi Performed by the Orchestra of the Academia di Santa Cecelia, Conductor Alberto Erede, December 10, 1959 (3) (Box 4)
  - I Pagliacci –Leoncavallo Performed by the Robert Shaw Chorale and the RCA Victor Orchestra, Conductor Renato Cellini (2) (Box 4)
  - Parsifal –Wagner Performed by the Bayreuth Festival Orchestra and Chorus, Conductor Hans Knappertsbuch, 1951 (Box 4)
  - Das Rheingold –Wagner Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Georg Solti (3) (Box 4)
  - Das Rheingold –Wagner Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Georg Solti (2) (Box 4)
  - Rigoletto –Verdi Performed by the Sinfonica di Torino della Radiotelevisione Italiana e coro cetra, Conductor Angerlo Questa, November 12, 1962 (2) Two copies (Box 5)
  - Romeo et Juliette –Gounod Performed by the Orchestra of Theatre National de L’Opera Paris, Conductor Alberto Erede (3) (Box 5)
  - Der Rosenkavalier –R. Strauss Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, Conductor Erich Kleiber, June 22, 1959 (2) (Box 5)
  - Salome –R. Strauss Performed by the Metropolitan Opera Company, Conductor Joseph Rosenstock, February 17, 1962 (2) (Box 5)
  - Tchaikovsky Symphony #5, April 2, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Tijuana Brass (Box 5)
  - La Tosca –Puccini Performed by the Orchestra La Scala in Milan, Conductor Victor de Sabata (2) (Box 5)
  - La Traviata –Verdi Performed by the Orchestra and Chorus La Scala, Conductor Tullio Serafin, November 12, 1962 (2) Two copies (Box 5)
  - Tristan und Isolde –Wagner Performed by the London Philharmoin Orchestra, Conductor Wilhelm Furtwängler, December 12, 1959 (4) (Box 5)
  - Il Trovatore –Verdi Performed by the Robert Shaw Chorale and RCA Victor Orchestra, Conductor Renato Cellini, November 13, 1962 Two copies (Box 5)
  - Turandot –Puccini Performed by the Orchestra and Chorus of La Scala, Conductor Tullio Serafin (2) (Box 5)
  - Twelve (XII) O’Clock –Greta Keller, January 12, 1962 (Box 5)
  - Un Ballo in Maschera –Verdi Performed by the New York Metropolitan Opera Company, Conductor Nello Santi, March 17, 1962 (2) (Box 5)
  - Luciano Virgili –Italian Popular Songs (Box 5)
  - Excerpts from Operas (2) (Box 5)
  - Wagner Opera –Commentary by John Culshaw, B.B.C. (Box 6)
  - Die Walküre –Wagner Performed by the Vienna Philharmonic, Conductor Wilhelm Furtwängler (4) (Box 6)
  - William Tell –Rossini Performed by the Orchestra and Chorus of Radio Italiana of Turin, Conductor Mario Rossi (3) (Box 6)
- Libretto Books
  - Adriana Lecouvreur –Metropolitan Opera, 1962
  - Ariadne on Naxos –Boosey & Hawkes, Inc., 1944
  - Andrea Chenier –Fred Rullman, Inc, 1954
  - Arabella –Metropolitan Opera, 1955
  - Don Pasquale –Grand Opera Librettos, Theodore Presser Company, undated
  - Fidelio –Light Opera Librettos, Oliver Ditson Company, undated
  - Faust –Official Libretto, undated
  - La Forza del Destino –Boosey & Hawkes, 1944
  - La Forza del Destino –Fred Rullman, Inc., 1952
  - Gianni Schicchi –G. Ricordi & Company, 1918
  - The Gypsy Baron –G. Schirmer, Inc., 1959
  - Lucia di Lammermoor –Oliver Ditson Company, undated
  - Lucia di Lammermoor –Metropolitan Opera, 1951
  - Lohengrin –Metropolitan Opera, 1951
  - Macbeth –Official Libretto, Fred Rullman, Inc., 1958
  - Madame Butterfly –Metropolitan Opera, 1954
  - Madame Butterfly –G. Ricordi & Company, 1907
  - The Magic Flute (Die Zauberflöte) –Grand Opera Librettos, Oliver Ditson Company, 1913
  - Manon –Grand Opera Librettos, Oliver Ditson Company, undated
  - Manon Lescaut –G. Ricordi & Company, 1893
  - Marta –Grand Opera Librettos, Oliver Ditson Company, undated
  - Mignon –Grand Opera Librettos, Oliver Ditson Company, undated
  - Nabucco –Metropolitan Opera, 1960
  - Norma –Metropolitan Opera, undated
  - Le Nozze di Figaro –G. Schirmer, Inc., 1959
  - Le Nozze di Figaro –Metropolitan Opera, 1959
  - Otello –Grand Opera Librettos, Oliver Ditson Company, undated
  - Otello –Metropolitan Opera, undated
  - Pagliacci –G. Schirmer’s Collection of Opera-Librettos, 1907
  - Das Rheingold –Metropolitan Opera, undated
  - Rigoletto –Official Libretto, Fred Rullman, Inc., 1952
  - Romeo et Juliette –Grand Opera Librettos, Oliver Ditson Company, 1911
  - Der Rosenkavalier –Metropolitan Opera, 1940
  - Salome –Metropolitan Opera, undated Siegfried –Metropolitan Opera
  - Siegfried –Metropolitan Opera, 1960
  - Simon Boccanegra –Official Libretto, 1931
  - Simon Boccanegra –Metropolitan Opera, 1931
  - Tosca –G. Schirmer’s Collection of Opera Librettos, 1956
  - Tosca –Metropolitan Opera, 1956 (2)
  - La Traviata –Metropolitan Opera, 1950
  - La Traviata –Official Libretto, 1950
  - Il Trovatore –Official Libretto, 1959
  - Turandot –G. Ricordi & Company, 1926
  - Die Walküre –Official Libretto, undated
  - Die Walküre –Metropolitan Opera, undated
  - William Tell (Guglielmo Tell) –Grand Opera Librettos, Oliver Ditson Company, undated
  - Wozzeck –Metropolitan Opera, 1931